♪♪
-T-minus 10, 9, 8, 7, 6...
We have main engine start.
4, 3, 2...
-All right.
-And liftoff!
Liftoff of the 25th
space shuttle mission,
and it has cleared the tower.
-Whoa!
-Wow!
[ Radio chatter ]
-Roger, roll, Challenger.
-Oh, wow.
-Good roll program confirmed.
Challenger now
heading downrange.
-Wow!
-Oh, wow.
-Ohh!
-Engines beginning
throttling down now, at 94%.
Velocity,
2,257 feet per second.
Altitude, 4.3 nautical miles.
Downrange distance,
3 nautical miles.
-Challenger, go at throttle up.
-Roger. Go at throttle up.
[ Chatter ]
-Flight controllers here
looking very carefully
at the situation.
Obviously a major malfunction.
-A major malfunction?
-We have no downlink.
Reports from
the flight dynamics officer
indicate that the vehicle
apparently exploded.
-What?! What?!
-The vehicle has exploded!
-We are looking at checking
with the recovery forces
to see what can be done
at this point.
-What?
-The vehicle had exploded!
-Oh, please, don't say that.
[ Indistinct conversations ]
♪♪
-Up until the
Challenger accident,
NASA was a very untypical
government agency.
We were inventing
as we went along,
so you had a lot of freedom.
-It was viewed internationally
as a fantastic place.
The Apollo missions gave it
an aura of invincibility.
-4 minutes and 27 seconds to go
before the start
of this historic mission.
-The year was 1981,
and NASA was about to amaze
the world with Columbia,
a new spacecraft that pushed
the limits of imagination.
-They never before have sent
a spacecraft into orbit
that is going to come down
as a plane.
-Instead of using
a single rocket, like Apollo,
the shuttle was attached
to an external fuel tank
and two solid rocket boosters.
Each of the boosters
was constructed
of joined metal tubes,
and the field joints were sealed
with two rubber gaskets
called O-rings.
-Look at those huge engines
getting ready
to catapult this strange
assemblage off the earth.
-But all this technology
wasn't cheap,
and NASA had to come up
with a new funding model.
So Congress and NASA
decided the shuttle program
could pay its way
by carrying payloads into orbit.
-The Department of Defense,
private contractors
that wanted experiments
done in space
would pay them
to take them up on the shuttle.
-And unlike Apollo,
the shuttle system
was going to be
almost entirely reusable.
-They had to return
this hardware back into space
as rapidly as they could.
It wasn't long into the program
they realized that that process
was far more difficult
than they ever anticipated.
-They were under
constant pressure to launch.
-T-minus 10, 9, 8...
-I'm getting a few butterflies
myself right now.
-We've gone for
main engine start.
We have main engine start.
♪♪
[ Indistinct shouting ]
-Go!
-Fly like an eagle.
♪♪
-Columbia was
a fantastic success,
but NASA had to figure out
how to make these
technological feats routine.
-They predicted,
in the beginning,
that they would be able
to launch 60 shuttles a year,
that NASA would, in fact, become
self-paying or self-funded.
-We had two pads up and running,
so you'd have two vehicles
out on the pad,
and they were going to launch,
like, three days apart.
-But that really never happened.
It was an experimental
technology,
and they just couldn't manage
that many,
so they continually fell behind.
-The shuttle program never had
more than nine launches
in a single year.
-We have a beautiful picture
now. It's coming through.
-And to help meet
their ambitious schedules,
NASA worked with
private contractors
to build many
of the shuttle's systems,
while NASA engineers
analyzed data
to see how well
everything performed.
-NASA kept very good records
of anomalies.
The problem is, is that
they ran into a lot of these.
-One thing engineers saw
was the O-rings that sealed
the booster joints
weren't behaving
according to design.
On several flights, especially
those at cold temperatures,
rocket propellant had blown
by the primary O-ring.
-The first time it happened,
they accepted it.
They tested it.
They thought they knew
what had happened.
And then, the next launch,
everything worked,
and then a few more launches,
and it happened again.
-But each time,
the secondary O-ring
prevented gases from escaping
the side of the booster.
So rather than stalling the
program to redesign the joint,
NASA waived the requirements
governing O-rings,
which effectively
made it acceptable
to fly with minimal erosion.
-Even with the worst O-ring
erosion they'd ever had,
it hadn't failed,
so they started to work on it,
but they really weren't rushing.
It didn't seem so terrible,
but they continually expanded
the bounds of acceptable risk.
-And then came
the 10th Challenger launch
and a mission unlike
any NASA had attempted before.
-They decided to make that
the first flight
that a ordinary citizen
could fly,
and that drew a tremendous
interest from the public,
plus the school systems
were going to show this
live on television.
-At this time,
I'd like to introduce you
to perhaps the person
you came to see,
and that's Christa McAuliffe,
our payload specialist,
teacher in space.
-My job at the time of
the Challenger was the director
of the space shuttle
solid-rocket motor project
for my company, Morton Thiokol.
-Morton Thiokol
was an engineering firm
out of Brigham City, Utah,
and had the NASA contract
to build the shuttle boosters.
-Well, I am so excited
to be here,
and I just hope everybody
tunes in on day four, now,
to watch the teacher
teaching from space.
-On the day before Challenger,
there was an overnight low
that was record-breaking.
-Got a telephone call
from one of the program managers
back in Utah that worked for me.
And he said, "Al," he says,
"We just heard
that it might get down
to as low as 18 degrees
by tomorrow morning."
"Good grief," I said.
"I'm really worried
about these O-ring seals
being able to operate properly
at those kind of temperatures."
-The mission had already
been rescheduled
after routine delays,
so now Morton Thiokol and NASA
scheduled an emergency
teleconference
the night before the launch.
-The engineers at Thiokol
were very concerned,
so they began scrambling
to put together an analysis
of temperature data.
-Larry Mulloy
was NASA's project manager
for the solid-rocket boosters.
-Then we went out
to the teleconference,
and Roger Boisjoly,
who was kind of the O-ring czar
at Morton Thiokol,
did most of the talking.
The recommendation
was that we wait
until it's 54 degrees
before we launch.
So I said something like,
"54 degrees where?"
-They had never drawn
a temperature line before,
and it meant a tremendous change
to the shuttle's schedule.
-It isn't what
they wanted to hear.
In fact, Larry made a comment,
"Thiokol, when the hell do you
want me to launch, next April?"
-Thiokol's engineers in Utah
were caught off guard
by NASA's strong reaction
to their recommendation,
so they asked if they could have
some time off the teleconference
to review the data in private.
-After they went offline,
Al McDonald was visibly upset,
and he said, "I wouldn't want
to be the guy that had to appear
at a board of inquiry
if this thing blows."
And I said,
"I understand that, Al.
And you won't have to.
That'll be me."
♪♪
-At Thiokol, the vice president
was asking those engineers
to stand up for what they said.
Roger Boisjoly took the lead
in the objections.
He said,
"I can't prove it to you.
All I know is that
it's away from goodness
in our experience base."
But the engineers at Thiokol
didn't have the data,
so the vice president
took the decision-making
away from the engineers
and asked the managers
to decide.
-And they did.
More than 30 minutes after
the engineers had gone offline,
Thiokol managers voted to
reverse the recommendation
and to launch the Challenger
as planned.
The teleconference
became a focal point
for the White House-appointed
Rogers Commission
that investigated NASA
after the disaster.
-There was not one positive
statement for launch
ever made in that room.
-What was driving you here?
What was to be achieved
that caused you to go?
♪♪
-NASA pressured the folks
at Thiokol to change their mind,
and it was clear to me
that we finally came back
and gave them
what they wanted to hear.
-You know,
we'd been rationalizing
this erosion
since the second flight.
-None of the information
the NASA managers were getting
was new.
This was not individuals
getting used to something.
This was organizationally
supported.
-That's where...
the accident was inevitable.
-Once Thiokol reversed
their initial recommendation,
someone needed to sign off
on the launch rationale.
-I did the smartest thing
I ever did in my lifetime.
I refused to sign it.
I just felt it was
too much risk to take.
-So just before midnight,
McDonald's boss,
Joe Kilminster,
signed off instead.
After the disaster,
the commission concluded
cold and joint design
were major factors
in Challenger's O-ring failure.
It also squarely
pointed a finger
at NASA managers like Mulloy.
-The commission did recognize
that there was
pressure to launch,
but they saw it as enacted
by amorally calculating managers
who were in positions
of responsibility.
I found something
completely different.
-So Vaughan began
her own investigation.
-No one wanted this to happen,
but intuition, you know,
"I don't feel good about this,"
should have been okay,
and they applied
all the usual rules
in a situation where
the usual rules didn't apply.
-4, 3, 2, 1.
♪♪
-We made a grievous error.
-So the real crux
of the matter is,
how do you get people
to recognize
when you need
to do something different
than what you've
been trained to do?
-After Challenger,
the Rogers Commission
prompted many changes at NASA,
including an increase
in the program's budget,
adding a third O-ring
to the booster joints,
and moving some managers,
including Mulloy,
out of the shuttle program.
-But there was nothing
really about
how to change the organization
that came out
of the commission report.
-And then in 2003,
after NASA had completed
15 years of successful missions,
came the 28th launch
of the Space Shuttle Columbia.
-It seemed like any other
launch, but, on the second day,
someone called me
on the phone and said,
"You've heard about the large
piece of debris or foam
that came off the tank
and hit the left wing,
caused a cloud, a poof?"
I said, "No, I didn't."
-Columbia made it into orbit
safely,
but the concern
was that if debris
had caused damage
to the left wing,
it could be vulnerable
on re-entry,
so just days after the launch,
NASA formed a special team
to assess the damage.
-The decision
to ask for more data,
the need for it, was unanimous.
-But management
was worried about
unnecessarily diverting Columbia
from its mission.
Since foam damage
had been generally considered
to be nonthreatening,
NASA manager Linda Ham
denied three requests
to get pictures
of the shuttle's underside
from a nearby satellite.
-And they were all put down
for different reasons.
The similarity between
Challenger and Columbia
was the falling back on routine
under uncertain circumstances.
-In the end, NASA sent
just one communication
to the astronauts
about the debris strike,
and on February 1, 2003,
the crew began
their return to Earth.
-Yeah. [ Laughs ]
-Part of our
engineering culture
is that you should work
to your chain of command.
I will regret, always,
why I didn't break the door down
by myself.
-And we're ready,
Willie, no deltas.
-Everything look good to you?
-I don't see anything
out of the ordinary.
-This is amazing.
It's really getting
fairly bright out there.
-They had just started
the de-orbit burn.
They were coming down, and
we started seeing temperatures
change higher on the left side
versus the right.
-FYI, I've just lost
four separate
temperature transducers
on the left side
of the vehicle.
-The anomalous data
confirmed my worst fear.
[ Radio static ]
-Columbia, Houston.
UHF comm check.
Columbia, Houston,
-I looked up, and I saw one of
our chief engineers in tears.
"We can't get the crew,"
she said.
"They've been incommunicado."
♪♪
"It happened. It happened."
-Columbia was destroyed
on re-entry.
♪♪
After the disaster,
Vaughan worked closely
with the Columbia Accident
Investigation Board,
which concluded that NASA
had ineffective leadership
and a flawed safety culture.
-We are quite convinced that
these organizational matters
are just as important
as the foam.
-Ham soon left
the shuttle program,
and NASA restructured
its management team.
-This happens in many different
kinds of organizations.
I don't think
that the general public
got the position
of either Larry Mulloy
or Linda Ham
and that their behavior was,
to a great deal,
determined by working in a very
rule-oriented organization.
[ Bell clanging ]
-Using her insights from NASA,
Vaughan developed a theory that
went beyond the space agency,
calling it
"normalization of deviance."
She says it helps explain
how, over time,
organizations come to accept
risky practices as normal.
-It's widespread...
with Katrina,
where the engineers were saying,
"These structures
are not going to hold.
We need to do
something more here,"
with British Petroleum,
early warning signs ignored.
-The cement used
in the Gulf oil rig was flawed.
[ Indistinct shouting ]
-The 2008 financial failure.
-The federal commission
concluded
it could have been avoided.
-You had a lot of
the heavy technology
derivatives and formulas,
and there is a fine line
between what is devious
and what's
a good business decision.
-And in 2017...
-Two deadly accidents
involving U.S. Navy ships.
-...the U.S. Navy
cited Vaughan's theory
to help explain accidents
that killed 17 sailors.
-We accepted this,
what was termed,
the normalization of deviance.
In other words, we allowed
our standards to drop,
thinking we were still okay.
♪♪
-We can never resolve
the problem of complexity,
but you have to be sensitive
to your organization
and how it works.
While a lot of us work
in complex organizations,
we don't really realize
the way the organizations
that we inhabit
completely inhabit us.
♪♪